Finding Aid for Elizabeth S. Brater papers, 1989-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Elizabeth S. Brater papers
1989-2010
1996-2010
Brater, Elizabeth S.
2011133 Aa 2; UAl
Member of the Michigan State Senate, House of Representatives, Ann Arbor City Council, and Mayor of Ann Arbor; records include handwritten notes on policy issues, collected research materials, and news clippings related to Brater’s service as a member of the Michigan State Senate and House of Representatives.
19.75 linear feet in 20 boxes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Elizabeth S. Brater (donor no. 10478 ) in 2011.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is closed to research until January 1, 2031.
Elizabeth Brater is a former member of the Michigan State Senate (2003-2010) and House of Representatives (1995-2000), Mayor of Ann Arbor (1991-1993) and member of the Ann Arbor City Council (1988-1993). She is a member of the Democratic Party. Prior to entering politics, Brater was a writer and editor and taught writing at the University of Michigan.
Brater is particularly well-known as a leader in the areas of the environment and mental health. As both a state Senator and Representative, Brater sponsored numerous bills focused on protecting the environment. She was named Sierra Club Environmentalist of the Year in 1996, Clean Water Action Great Lakes Lawmaker of the Year in 2005, Jane Elder Environmentalist of the Year in 2006, and received the Michigan League of Conservation Voters Environmental Leadership Award in 2004.
As a mental health advocate, Brater worked to ensure that people with mental illnesses were in treatment rather than in jail or homeless shelters. She received several awards for her work in this area as well, including the Michigan Alliance for the Mentally Ill Legislator of the Year Award and the Association of Children's Mental Health Legislator of the Year Award in 1998 and the Michigan Psychiatric Society Mental Health Advocate Award in 2000. During her years in the legislature, Elizabeth Brater focused a great deal of attention on the issue of the prevention of criminalization of people with mental illness (PWMI). Many people refer to this public policy issues as "jail diversion," but Brater felt this label was inaccurate. Jail diversion refers to diverting PWMI from the jail after they have already been arrested, while her policy objective was to prevent PWMI from being arrested in the first place though a series of preventative steps, such as educating law enforcement personnel about how to interact with PWMI and giving PWMI access to the mental health system. A second prevention stage, if arrest did occur, was the establishment of a mental health court to allow PWMI charged with a crime to be diverted to mental health treatment, rather than pursue the adjudication. She adopted the term Treatment Alternatives to describe this public policy objective.
In addition to her service at the state level, Brater was active in Ann Arbor city governance. She was elected as the first woman mayor in 1991, and represented Ann Arbor's Third Ward on the City Council from 1988 to 1991. As Mayor she secured passage of the city's weekly recycling collection program and led the effort to launch the city's materials recovery facility. She also worked to increase cooperation between Ann Arbor and its neighbors and improve the efficiency of city government.
Elizabeth Brater was born in Boston, Massachusetts in 1951 and graduated from the University of Pennsylvania with a B. A. in English (1973) and an M. A. in History (1976). She has been involved in many community and environmental organizations including the Sierra Club, the Ecology Center, and the League of Women Voters. She is married to Enoch Brater, and moved to Ann Arbor in 1975 when he accepted a position as an English professor at the University of Michigan. The Braters have two children who graduated from the Ann Arbor Public Schools.
The Brater collection consists of eight series: Environment and Natural Resources, Mental Health, Judiciary, Other Policy Files, Legislative Files, Subject Files, News Clippings, and Other Office Files. The collection's strength lies in its documentation of Brater's activities in the areas of environmental issues and mental illness treatment programs as a member of the Michigan Senate and House of Representatives.
Subjects:
Brater, Elizabeth S.; Michigan. Legislature. House of Representatives.; Michigan. Legislature. Senate.; Environmental law--Michigan.; Legislators--Michigan.; Mental health laws--Michigan.; Women legislators--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Michigan--Politics and government--1991-2000.; Michigan--Politics and government--2001-2010.
- Environment and Natural Resources
  The first series Environment and Natural Resources, documents Brater's work on behalf of environmental issues, including conservation, toxic waste, solid waste, and water use. The material includes Brater's notes, collected research materials, and copies of bills and amendments proposed in both the House and Senate. The series contains material organized according to topic, House and Senate legislative files, and a subseries of subject files organized alphabetically. The files cover Brater's service in both the House and Senate.
  - Land Use
    - General, 2002-2004 (Box 1)
    - Housing, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Presentations, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Public Comment Resources, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Final Report, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Traffic, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Mackinac Center, 1999-2003 (Box 1)
    - PDR Applications, Washtenaw, 2000; 2003 (Box 1)
    - Smart Growth, AFL-CIO, undated (Box 1)
    - Tax Credits for Easement, undated (Box 1)
    - Land Use Council, 2003; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Land Resource Project Presentation, undated (Box 1)
    - Dexter Township Citizens, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Land Use Partners, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Scio Township, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Legislation Priorities, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Planning, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Smart Growth, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Property Taxes to Preserve Farm, 2001-2008 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Coordinated Planning Act, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Intergovernmental, Southeast Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG), 1994 (Box 1)
    - Land Division Act and Other Land Use Legislation, 1999-2001; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Mobile Home Act, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Open Space Zoning Legislation, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Planning and Zoning, 1995-1997; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Septic, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Smart Growth, 2000-2001 (Box 2)
    - Cost of Development Report, University of Michigan School of Natural Resources, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Rights Market Program, undated (Box 2)
  - Solid Waste
    - Surcharge, 2003-2005 (Box 2)
    - Toronto, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Senate Democratic Bills, 2003 (Box 2)
    - House Bill, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Bill Package, 2004 (Box 2)
    - Washtenaw County, 2004 (Box 2)
    - Landfill Surcharge, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Tipping Fee, 2007 (Box 2)
    - General, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Landfill Capacity, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Recycling, 2004 (Box 2)
    - SB 783 and HBs 5176-78, Republican Solid Waste Package, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Water
    - SBs 850-852, Water Package, 2005; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - SB 851, Amending Natural Resources Act, 2005 (Box 2)
    - SB 852, Amending Natural Resources Act, 2005 (Box 2)
    - SB 854, Amending Natural Resources Act, 2005 (Box 2)
    - SB 857, Safe Drinking Water Act, 2005 (Box 2)
    - SBs 854-58, Democratic Package, 2005 (Box 2)
    - Water Legacy, 2004-2005; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - SBs 850-SB852, Amendments, 2005 (Box 2)
    - SBs 850-SB852, Democratic Amendments and Talking Points, 2005 (Box 2)
    - Original Bills and Committee Testimony, 2005 (Box 2)
    - HB 5875 Water Diversions Monitoring Fee Legislation, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Milliken Letter about Water Issue, 2008 (Box 2)
    - Water Legacy, Michigan Water Environment Association (MWEA) Talk, 2004-2005 (Box 3)
    - General, 2005-2006; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Town Hall Meetings, 2005 (Box 3)
    - SB 289, Aquifer Protection, 2003 (Box 3)
    - HB 4087 Moolinar Water Conflicts, 2003 (Box 3)
    - SB 289 Hearings, Research Materials, 1997; 2003 (Box 3)
    - Wetlands, 2003-2004 (Box 3)
    - Watersheds, 1996-1998 (Box 3)
    - Water Quality (Box 3)
    - Watershed Management, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Wetlands, 1994-2001 (Box 3)
  - Other Environmental Files
    - ACT 307 Sites, 1993-1995 (Box 4)
    - ACT 307, Polluters Pay "Reform" Plans, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Air Permit Fees, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - Air Quality, 1996-2007; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Air Quality, Ozone, 2005 (Box 4)
    - Air Quality, Ozone Attainment Areas, 2003-2004 (Box 4)
    - Air Quality, New Source, undated (Box 4)
    - Alternative Energy, 2005-2007; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - American Automobile Association, 2001 (Box 4)
    - Anti-Degradation, 2005 (Box 4)
    - Beach Grooming, 2003-2006; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Billboards, undated (Box 4)
    - Bills Referred, 2005 (Box 4)
    - Brownfield Authorities, 2003 (Box 4)
    - Budget, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Burning, 1996-1997 (Box 4)
    - Chester Meeting, 2003 (Box 4)
    - Children's Health, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - Children's Health Press Conference, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Children and the Environment, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - Chlorine Free Paper, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Clean Michigan Initiative (CMI) Funds, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
    - Clean Up Funding, 1996-1998 (Box 4)
    - Code, 1994 (Box 4)
    - Colt Farms, 2003 (Box 4)
    - Composting, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Concentrated Animal Feeding Operations (CAFOs), 2007 (Box 4)
    - Conservation Districts, undated (Box 4)
    - Decabromodiphenyl Ether (DECA), 2009 (Box 4)
    - Department of Environmental Quality Audits, 1992-1997 (scattered) (Box 4)
    - Department of Environmental Quality Budget, 2003-2005; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Department of Environmental Quality Enforcement, 1996-1999 (Box 4)
    - Department of Environmental Quality, General, 2004 (Box 4)
    - Department of Environmental Quality Organizational Chart, 2003-2006 (Box 4)
    - Department of Natural Resources Audits, 1991-1997 (Box 5)
    - Department of Natural Resources Clippings, 1993-1995 (Box 5)
    - Department of Natural Resources, Department Organization Chart, 1996-2003 (Box 5)
    - Department of Natural Resources General Information, 1995-1997; undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Department of Natural Resources Miscellaneous, 1995-1997 (Box 5)
    - Department of Natural Resources/PILT Budget, 2003 (Box 5)
    - Department of Natural Resources and Department of Environmental Quality Split, 1995; 2001 (Box 5)
    - Drain Code, 1998-2004; 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Dredging, 2000 (Box 5)
    - Earth Day Press Conference, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Endangered Species, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Energy, 1995-2009; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Energy Saving Appliances, 2006 (Box 5)
    - Enviro-Michigan Network Advocates, 1996 (Box 5)
    - Environment and Economics, 1998-2004 (Box 5)
    - Environmental Audits, 1997 (Box 5)
    - Environmental Bond, 1998; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Environmental Indicators (HB 4558), 1997-1998 (Box 5)
    - Environmental Justice, 1997-1998 (Box 5)
    - Environmental Science Board, 1998 (Box 5)
    - Environmental Strategy, 1996-2001; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Environmental Task Force, 1999-2004; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - ESB Priorities, 2009 (Box 5)
    - Farmland Preservation, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
    - Federal Funding, 1995 (Box 6)
    - Fertilizer (HB 5866), 1998 (Box 6)
    - Flow Control, 1996 (Box 6)
    - Forestry, 1997 (Box 6)
    - General, 1990-2003; 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Global Warming, 1997-1999 (Box 6)
    - Grand Haven Aquatic Research, 1996 (Box 6)
    - Granholm Platform, 2003 (Box 6)
    - Great Lakes Basin Water Resources, undated (Box 6)
    - Great Lakes Charter Annex, 2001; undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Great Lakes, General, 1995-2002; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Great Lakes Initiative, 1995-1998 (Box 6)
    - Great Lakes Restoration, undated (Box 6)
    - Great Lakes Science Center, 1995-1996; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Great Lakes Water Quality Bond, 2002; 2005 (Box 6)
    - Green Chemistry, 2006 (Box 6)
    - Green Scissors, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Greenway Proposal, 2003 (Box 6)
    - Groundwater, 1997 (Box 6)
    - Groundwater Advisory Council Report, 2006 (Box 6)
    - Groundwater Pollution Prevention, 1995 (Box 6)
    - Hazardous Waste, 1996-1998 (Box 6)
    - Hazardous Waste Inspection, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Higgins Lake, 1993 (Box 6)
    - Indicators, 2003 (Box 6)
    - Injection Wells, 1999 (Box 6)
    - Introduced Bills, 2006 (Box 6)
    - Jordan River, 1996-1998 (Box 6)
    - Lab Accreditation, 2004 (Box 7)
    - Lake Michigan Drilling, 1997 (Box 7)
    - Land Consolidation, 2006 (Box 7)
    - Landfill Moratorium, 1997 (Box 7)
    - Law Overview and Summary, 2009 (Box 7)
    - Leaking Underground Storage Tank (LUST), 1996-2001 (Box 7)
    - Mercury, 2004-2006 (Box 7)
    - Mercury, Electric Utility Workgroup, 2005 (Box 7)
    - Michigan Rivers, 1997 (Box 7)
    - Michigan Underground Storage Tank Financial Assurance Fund (MUSTFA), 1995 (Box 7)
    - Michigan United Conservation Clubs (MUCC), 1999-2000 (Box 7)
    - Mining, undated (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1993-1995 (Box 7)
    - Multi-pollutant Work Group Conference Call, 2006 (Box 7)
    - National Caucus of Environmental Legislation, 1996-1997 (Box 7)
    - National Conference of State Legislatures (NCSL) Positions, 1995 (Box 7)
    - National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System, 2003-2004 (Box 7)
    - Natural Resources, 2003 (Box 7)
    - Natural Resources Trust Fund, 1996-1997; 2003; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Natural Rivers, 1997 (Box 7)
    - Non-ferrous Metallic Mining, 2004 (Box 7)
    - Non-Point Source Pollution, 1998 (Box 7)
    - Nordhouse Dunes, 1995-1997 (Box 7)
    - Nuclear Energy, undated (Box 7)
    - Nuclear Waste, 1996-1999 (Box 7)
    - Oil and Gas Gaylord Meeting, 1997-1998; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Ozone, 1997-2001 (Box 7)
    - Ozone Transport, 1998 (Box 7)
    - Parks, 2003 (Box 7)
    - Parks and Recreation Association, 2005 (Box 7)
    - Part 201, 1994-1999 (scattered) (Box 7)
    - Part 201, Baseline Environmental Assessments, 2003 (Box 7)
    - Part 201, Dow, undated (Box 7)
    - PBDEs (Polybrominated diphenol ethers), 2008; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Pesticides, 1992-1998 (Box 7)
    - Phosphorus, 2002-2003; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Pickerel Lake, 2004 (Box 7)
    - Pollution Prevention, 1992-1999; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Pollution Prevention Correspondence, 1995 (Box 8)
    - Polychlorniated biphenyls (PCBs) Landfill, 1997 (Box 8)
    - Press Packet, 1997 (Box 8)
    - PILT Agreement, 2004 (Box 8)
    - Radon, 1993-1999 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - Recycling, 1995; 2001 (Box 8)
    - Recycling, 4-H, 2006 (Box 8)
    - Referred Bills, 2003-2006 (Box 8)
    - RRS Recycling Project, 1996 (Box 8)
    - Scant Oil Drilling, 2001 (Box 8)
    - Scrap Tires, 1998-2004 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - Sierra Club Lobby Day, 2005 (Box 8)
    - Solid Waste, 1996-1997; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Solid Waste Flow Control, 1994 (Box 8)
    - Solid Waste Landfill Capacity, 1996-1997 (Box 8)
    - Solid Waste, Out of State, 1996-1999 (Box 8)
    - Solid Waste, Trash Can, 1997 (Box 8)
    - Southeast Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG) Environment Committee, 1998 (Box 8)
    - Sludge, 1997; 2001; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - State of the Huron Conference, 2005 (Box 9)
    - Strategy and Business Arguments, 2003 (Box 9)
    - Storm Water, 1997 (Box 9)
    - Surface Water, 1995-1997 (Box 9)
    - Takings Bill, 1995 (Box 9)
    - Task Force Hearing, 2004 (Box 9)
    - Tax Code, 1997 (Box 9)
    - Tax Credit, Pollution Control Devices, 2004 (Box 9)
    - Toxics, 1997-2001 (Box 9)
    - Urban Caucus, 1998-1999 (Box 9)
    - Urban Core Mayors, 1994 (Box 9)
    - Use Variance, 2006 (Box 9)
    - Water, Ann Arbor, 2004 (Box 9)
    - Water Use and Conversation, 2004 (Box 9)
    - Yardwaste, 1996-1997 (Box 9)
  - Other Environmental Legislation
    - House Bills
      - HB 4617 Dow Facilities, 2005 (Box 9)
      - Natural Resources and Environmental Protection Act
        - HB 5284, 1997 (Box 9)
        - HB 5284/4037, 1997 (Box 9)
        - HB 5284/4034, 1997 (Box 9)
        - HB 4037, 1997-1998; 2 folders (Box 9)
        - HB 4596, 1995-1996; 5 folders (Box 10)
        - HB 5154, 2004 (Box 10)
        - HB 4558, 1996-1997 (Box 10)
    - Senate Bills
      - SB 4
        - Compulsory Education, 2007 (Box 10)
        - Solid Waste, 1997 (Box 10)
      - SB 152, Phosphorous and Other Contaminants, 2008 (Box 10)
      - Natural Resources and Environmental Protection Act
        - SB 252, Natural Resources and Environmental Protection Act, 2003 (Box 10)
        - SBs 46 and 568, 2003 (Box 10)
        - SB 833, 2003 (Box 10)
        - SB 282, 2003 (Box 10)
      - SB 560, Groundwater Discharge, 2004 (Box 10)
      - SBs 805 and 806, Clean Michigan Initiative (CMI)-Brownfields, 2003; 2 folders (Box 10)
      - SB 728, Environmental Audit, 1997 (Box 10)
      - SB 840, Phosphorous, 2006 (Box 10)
      - SB 722, Pollution Prevention, 2004 (Box 10)
      - SB 1432 Watershed Alliance, 2004 (Box 10)
      - SB 332, Aquatic Nuisance Species Ballast, 2005 (Box 10)
      - SB 651, Soil Erosion, 1999 (Box 10)
      - SB 250-253, National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System (NPDES), 2003 (Box 10)
      - SB 1177 Fracking, 2010 (Box 10)
- Mental Health
  The second series, Mental Health, documents Brater's efforts on behalf of improved state mental health services. Materials in the series include notes and research materials on topics related to mental health in prisons, community mental health, children, treatment alternatives, and a FOIA request related to jail diversion programs. Material is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General Information
    - 2000 (Box 11)
    - (earlier published material), 2001 (Box 11)
    - 2002 (Box 11)
    - 2004 (Box 11)
  - Housing, 2002 (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan School of Social Work Commencement Speech, 2007 (Box 11)
  - Alliance for the Mentally Ill (AMI) Lawsuit, 1999 (Box 11)
  - Audits, 1993-2000 (Box 11)
  - Budget, 1998-2000; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Brain Injury, 1997 (Box 11)
  - Children, 1995-2000 (scattered) (Box 11)
  - Commission, Mental Health, 2003 (Box 11)
  - Community Mental Health
    - Services Waiver, 1998 (Box 11)
    - Bid Out, 1999-2000 (Box 11)
    - Task Force, 1997-1999 (Box 11)
  - Concept Paper, Bid Out, 1998-2000; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Carve Out, 2009 (Box 11)
  - Children, Better Access to Mental Health Services, 2000-2003 (Box 11)
  - Code Revision, 1995 (Box 11)
  - Corrections
    - General, 1995-2010 (scattered); 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Prisons, 1997-2003 (Box 11)
    - Courts, 2007 (Box 12)
  - Community Mental Health
    - General, 1996-1997 (Box 12)
    - Formula, 2009 (Box 12)
    - Washtenaw County, 1997-1998 (Box 12)
    - Washtenaw County Spend Down, 1999 (Box 12)
  - Committee Information, 1996-1998 (Box 12)
  - Criminalization
    - Forensic Center, 2007-2008; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Not Guilty by Reason of Insanity (NGRI), undated (Box 12)
  - Health Care Financing Administration (HCFA) Video Conference, 2000 (Box 12)
  - Home Health Waiver, undated (Box 12)
  - Hospital Closures, 1997-1999; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Federal, 2000 (Box 12)
  - Times Letter, 1999 (Box 12)
  - Jail
    - Diversion, 1999 (Box 12)
    - Survey, 1998 (Box 12)
    - Survey and FOIA Request, 1999; 4 folders (Box 12)
  - Department of Mental Health, 1995 (Box 12)
  - Managed Care, 1996-1998 (Box 12)
  - Managed Care for Profit, undated (Box 12)
  - Medicaid Eligible Services, 1996-2000 (Box 12)
  - Mental Illness, General Information, 1999-2000 (Box 12)
  - Mental Illness and the Criminal Justice System, 2000-2004 (Box 12)
  - Mental Health Independent Study, 2009 (Box 13)
  - Mt. Pleasant Center Closure, 2009 (Box 13)
  - Conversion of Old State Hospital, 2003 (Box 13)
  - Mental Health Code, 1995-1996 (Box 13)
  - Mentality, 1999 (Box 13)
  - National Alliance for the Mentally Ill (NAMI), Washtenaw County, 2005 (Box 13)
  - Parity
    - Background, 1999-2000; 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Clips, 1998-2000 (Box 13)
    - Work Group, 1998-2000 (Box 13)
    - Coalition, 1998 (Box 13)
  - Person Requiring Treatment, 2005 (Box 13)
  - Psychiatry, 1995-2000 (scattered); 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Press Project, 1997-2000 (Box 13)
  - Taskforce Hearing, 1999 (Box 13)
  - Trailblazers, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Washtenaw County Community Health Organization, 2000 (Box 13)
  - Work Group, 2004 (Box 13)
  - Treatment Alternatives
    - Background, 1997-2005; 6 folders (Box 13)
    - Police Training
      - Background, 1997-2009 (Box 13)
      - Prevention of Criminalization, 2010-2011 (Box 13)
    - Criminal Procedure, 1999 (Box 13)
    - Prevention of Criminalization, undated (Box 13)
    - Mental Health Court Bills, 1997-1999 (Box 13)
    - Mental Health Courts, 1999-2009 (scattered) (Box 13)
    - Excluded Offenses, 2007 (Box 13)
    - Mental Health Courts Feedback, 2007 (Box 13)
    - Kevin's Law, 2004-2005 (Box 13)
    - Mack Article (Probate), 2006-2008 (Box 13)
    - Jail Diversion Materials from Gains Center, 1996-1997 (Box 14)
    - Diversion Budget, 2007 (Box 14)
    - Prison Privatization, 2007 (Box 14)
    - Department of Corrections and Department of Health, 2006 (Box 14)
    - Courts
      - General, 2007-2008 (Box 14)
      - Funding, 2007 (Box 14)
      - Bills SB171-172, 2007 (Box 14)
      - House Bill 4627, 1996-1997 (Box 14)
    - Press Conferences
      - 1998 (Box 14)
      - 1999 (Box 14)
      - 2000 (Box 14)
    - Speech, undated (Box 14)
    - Jail Survey, 1997-1998 (Box 14)
    - Revised Treatment Alternatives Bill, 1998 (Box 14)
    - Studies, 1997-2000 (Box 14)
    - Conference, 2007 (Box 14)
    - "Criminalizing the Mentally Ill: The Abuse of Jails as Mental Hospitals,", 1992 (Box 14)
    - Taskforce, 2000 (Box 14)
    - Corrections, 2007; 2009 (Box 14)
    - Clippings, 1997-2000; 2 folders (Box 14)
- Judiciary
  Judiciary, the third series, contains files related to Brater's service on the State Senate's Judiciary Committee. The files document Brater's positions on issues ranging from prisons to sexual assault laws.
  - General, 2003 (Box 15)
  - Adoption, 2003-2004; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - SB1123 Asbestos, 2006 (Box 15)
  - HB4247 Blood Alcohol Content, 2003 (Box 15)
  - SR304, Caro Center, 2004 (Box 15)
  - Choice (Abortion Rights), 2003 (Box 15)
  - Civil Liberties, 2003 (Box 15)
  - Corrections
    - Correspondence, 2003 (Box 15)
    - Clippings, 2006 (Box 15)
    - Prisons, 2004 (Box 15)
    - SB1388 Out of State Placement for Juvenile Delinquents, 2004 (Box 15)
    - Mental Health Care in Prison, 2006 (Box 15)
    - Prison Population Projections, 2006 (Box 15)
    - Abuse of Women Prisoners, 2003 (Box 15)
    - Truth in Sentencing, 2003 (Box 15)
    - Prisoner Re-entry, 2005 (Box 15)
  - Domestic Violence, 1994; 2005 (Box 15)
  - Drug Courts, 2004 (Box 15)
  - Foster Care, 2004 (Box 15)
  - SB1046 Gun Package, 2000-2006 scattered; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - SB 309, Identity Theft, 2003-2005; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Identity Theft Clippings, 1999-2001 (Box 15)
  - SB637, Minor in Possession, 2003; 2009; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Internet Dating, 2005 (Box 15)
  - SR/HR77, Resolution to Condemn Terrorism, 2003 (Box 15)
  - SB212 and 788, Judicial Assignments, 2003 (Box 15)
  - Juvenile Justice and Interrogation, 2000 (Box 15)
  - Marriage/Public Policy, 2004 (Box 15)
  - SB542-95 and HB4796 Preliminary Exams, 2005-2006 (Box 15)
  - SB648-652, Methamphetamines, 2003 (Box 15)
  - Selepak Case (Parole Violation), 2006 (Box 15)
  - Prisoner Treatment Programs, 2005-2006 (Box 15)
  - Public Defender, 2001 (Box 15)
  - Sexual Assault Bills, undated (Box 15)